<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Example of Gods iudgement shew[n] vpon two children borne in high Dutch la[nd] in the citie of Lutssolof, the first day of Iulie and translated out of Dutche into Englishe the 6. Nouember last / by Cornelius Pet.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10608.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122315</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22919457</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22919457</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25895</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25895)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 379:2 or 1777:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Example of Gods iudgement shew[n] vpon two children borne in high Dutch la[nd] in the citie of Lutssolof, the first day of Iulie and translated out of Dutche into Englishe the 6. Nouember last / by Cornelius Pet.</title>
                  <author>Pet, Cornelius.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9] p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For VVilliam Bartlet and are to be solde at S. Magnus corner by Richard Ballard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1582?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint taken from colophon; date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]2 B3.</note>
                  <note>T.p. contains illustration.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with print show-through and pages cropped with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peace --  Religious aspects.</term>
               <term>Repentance.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25895:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:25895:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <p>¶ <hi>An example of Gods iudgement shew<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> vpon two Children borne in high <hi>Dutch La<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the Citie of <hi>Lutſſolof,</hi> the firſt day of <hi>Iulie.</hi> and tranſlated out of Dutche into Engliſhe the <hi>6.</hi> Nouember laſt by <hi>Cornelius Pet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25895:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:25895:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eerly beloued Bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren like as daily wee ſee the wunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous woorks of GOD, to aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe vs to the amendment of our ſinful wicked &amp; deteſtable liues, be fore hee dooth plague vs, like as alwaiſe hee is good and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and doth not puniſh vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto our deſarts, but ſendeth vs firſt Signes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to admo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſh vs of his ire whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch wee ſo rightly deferne for our ſo little regarding &amp; eſteeming of his moſt holy woord and goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. But wee dayly neglecting and not regarding the ſame.</p>
            <p>Hee therfore hath not only ſent hydeous Monſters and fearfull Signes, vnto thoſe where they were borne and ſeen: but aſwel vnto vs, yea and rather vnto vs becauſe wee hauing the ſincere
<pb facs="tcp:25895:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->Doctrine and Goſpel of Chriſte ſo vnfeinedly preached yea ſo er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſtly ſet foorth and ſo dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vtterd, and yet wee nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. But like ſtubburn and obſtinate Children run hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into our damnation.</p>
            <p>Wherfore wee haue to giue the greater account of the time which wee haue ſpent (when we ſhall come and appeer before the Iudgement ſeat of GOD the moſte rightful Iudge) wherfore deerly belouid let vs not be like thoſe of <hi>Sodome, Gomorra, Ieruſalem,</hi> and many other Cities which would not eſteem of the tokens and ſignes which God ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>But let vs repent with thoſe of <hi>Niniuie,</hi> and pray vnto GOD for mercy and humble our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m then wil hee not extend his wrath vpon vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but be mercifull vnto vs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25895:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <head>The Diſcription of two ſtrange Children.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Childe (deerly Belooued, which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt figured before the heer, was born the day and yeet a boone written, beeing in alll pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portion as thou ſeeſt it heer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. The hed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Childe was to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared in all points like vnto a Biſhops Miter, In all other points wel proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſaue the hands which were as the Picture dooth repreſent the right hand a ſwoord, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> left hand a rod, the other points firmable as a Childe ought to be, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Coullour of this Child was to be compared vnto a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro,</hi> or Blackmore, (the which Childe) liued the ſpace of three dayes, in the which dayes it did moſte wunderouſly ſpeak theſe woords following.</p>
            <p>Be the warres of men not yet
<pb facs="tcp:25895:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->doon? Make peace, Make peace in all Cuntries for the LORD wil come and puniſh the Earth, with Swoord and Rod, as my hands doo repreſent. And alſo hee ſaid amend you in all Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries for there wil ſuch a mortali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie come, yea ſuch a ſudain death that one ſhall ſay vnto an other / Oh, Brother where haue you been that you are not dead? Theſe were the woords of the firſt Childe, which as I haue ſaid before is heer portraturde vnto thee. Therfore repent of thy former offences.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25895:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
               <head>The Diſcription of the other Childe.</head>
               <head>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25895:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
               <pb facs="tcp:25895:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
               <head>The diſcription of the other Childe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He other Childemy belooued / had this proportion, that is to ſay. It had two heads in good four<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, but that it was vpon the one ſide very black / like as the other was. And the other white, and as good c<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>let as may be, and nothing to be ſeene in the propor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion that ſeemed ſtraunge, but only black and white. This o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Childe liued alſo three day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. It did <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ure reſt but contiou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly did cry and weep and made great lamentation. In ſo much that euery one Lamented to ſee this pitious ſpectakle, and the third day they bothe dyed.</p>
               <p>Theſe Children were borne in <hi>Lutſolof,</hi> foure miles diſtant from <hi>Sir<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>rach,</hi> in the which Cittye, the ſame was firſt publiſhed, to
<pb facs="tcp:25895:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->the great comfort of the Godly  / and to the wicked a terrour and greefe of minde.</p>
               <p>The Father of theſe Children was named <hi>Baltus Maler,</hi> and the Mother that hare them / had to name <hi>Katherin Peeters,</hi> who was of the age of fortye yeeres when ſhe bare them.</p>
               <p>At the time of their death, fell ſuch a greeuous Plague amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them of the Cittie: that there dyed in nyne dayes two thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand perſons. Wherof ſome dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſitting at meat, &amp; with meat in their mouthes. And the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was of ſo much abundance that it periſhed vpon the Ground for lack of thoſe that ſhould gather it in for the people lay in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreets as moſſe or durt, and there durſt none gather it in.</p>
               <p>There haue ſome ſuppoſed this to be but lyes and fables.
<pb facs="tcp:25895:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->but indeed they are the very han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy woorks of God and I would wiſh thoſe Vnbeleeuers to be ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertiſed from their vnbeleef and forſake their ſinnes, leaſt when it is to late they doo repent.</p>
               <p>Wee haue a fearful beginning amongſt vs of <hi>Louin,</hi> of <hi>Maſtreicht</hi> of <hi>Aken,</hi> at <hi>Namure,</hi> at <hi>Sitteret,</hi> &amp; at <hi>Antvverp,</hi> where the People dyed of the plague by heapes, for there hath dyed of the plague co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly three hundred a week.</p>
               <p>Thus wiſhing you Chriſtian Bretheren to take example by our plagues to receiue the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpel of our Lorde and forſake your ſins, I bid you Farwel.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London for VVilliam Bartlet</hi> and are to be ſolde at S. Magnus cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner by <hi>Richard Ballard.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25895:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:25895:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
